<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<sect1 id="requirements">
  <title>Requirements</title>
  <authorblurb>
    <para>by <ulink url="mailto:jbank@arsdigita.com">Joseph Bank</ulink>, 
    <ulink url="mailto:joel@aufrecht.org">Joel Aufrecht</ulink></para>
  </authorblurb>

  <sect2 id="gatekeeper-requirements-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para> Gatekeeper allows an OpenACS installation to provide users
    authenticated access to other web sites.  This is particularly
    useful for dealing with "mounting" another legacy website on our
    own site, while adding a security layer.  We can then only allow
    access to the legacy website from the main ACS server.  </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gatekeeper-overview">
    <title>System/Application Overview</title>
    
    <para>Gatekeeper provides an application for managing seamless
    remote viewing of other web pages with optional security layers.
    It consists of the following components:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>A web interface for retrieving foreign urls.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>An API for adding security restrictions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="gatekeeper-use-cases">
    <title>Use-cases and User Scenarios</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para> Jane Webmaster wants to build an ACS site that provides paid
      access to a currently existing web site.  This other site uses
      significantly different technology, so full integration would
      require a great deal of effort.  </para>
      <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para>Jane creates an instance of the gatekeeper package which points to the existing site.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para>She sets up a security restriction for the gatekeeper instance using
            ACS permissions by only allowing read access for a newly created
            user group.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>She modifies the ACS Ecommerce system to insert and remove users from the new user group based on their subscription payments.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>She modifies the existing site to only serve requests from her ACS server's IP address.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <programlisting>
--------------------------------------------
Use case
--------------------------------------------

Integration of an external web mail client: Squirrelmail (PHP-based) and
IMAP-Server.

Administrator
--------------------------------------------
The institution has to have an IMAP server up and running. OpenACS must
be installed using the external authentication via pam-imap/ldap/passwd
(etc.) to authenticate and synchronize openacs users.

The administrator has to have a webmail client like IMP or Squirrelmail
installed on Apache+PHP. The AOLServer has to have access to Apache for
instance over localhost.

The administrator has sucessfully installed the external authentication
package using pam.

The administrator has to do the following to integrate the external
webmail client squirrelmail using the gatekeeper.

1. Create a new Gatekeeper Instance: Name: Squirrelmail
2. Indicate the required parameters for the gatekeeper instance:
- URL to guard:
http://localhost/squirrel/
- Gatekeeper Type:

requires external authentication
- Path to an optional header/footer template
/www/service0/packages/dotlrn/dotlrn-master.adp
- Name of the authority used (local, pam, ldap...) or database table
with account informations:
pam
- used login form input field:
login_username
- used password form input field:
secretkey
- logout/sign-out path:
http:/localhost/squirrel/src/signout.php
- request method:
post
- form action:
http:/localhost/squirrel/redirect.php
- where to add the startpage of the webmail in openacs:
/dotlrn/?&amp;page-num=3

The timeout of squirrelmail has to be set to a higher value than that of
OpenACS to make sure that the webmail session is valid as long as the
OpenACS session is valid.


Gatekeeper
--------------------------------------------
The Gatekeeper Instance registers itself for auto logon on to that
authority. Thus after a sucessful login the login information is also
used to login to the webmail client and the cookies are forwarded to the
users browser. Thus the authentication package has to be extended for
post-login and logout procedure-calls. On request the gatekeeper checks
the content type (html, xhtml, compressed or not, usage of frames or
not) and rewrites the links apropriately. As soon as the user logs out
the webmail client is also logged out.

User
--------------------------------------------
The user simply logs into the system once and is served a link where he
can access the webmail-client. In this case over My Space-->My Mails as
Page three under dotLRN. The documentation of the webmail client has to

be made accessible to the user.

The current Gatekeeper has to be improved by the following:
- allow usage of templates (done already)
- allow xml, xhtml
- allow compressed data
- auto-check of frames --> if frames are used then the template is
useless or the frame has to be embedded inside another frameset.
- cookies forwarding for external application (not sure if that already
exists)

Restrictions
--------------------------------------------
- Different locale between OpenACS and Webmail
- Different designs (depending on the webmail client this can be changed
via templates).
- no true integration into MySpace possible to notify user that she/he
has new unread emails.
</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <programlisting>
--------------------------------------------
Other Use-Case:
--------------------------------------------
Integration of PHPWiki (xhtml) via Gatekeeper and LDAP/PAM/SQL...

Username Inputfield: auth[userid]
Password Inputfield: auth[passwd]
Form action:    HomePage?action=browse
For OpenACS-Authority: PAM
PHPWiki can use many different types of authentication: LDAP, IMAP,
PASSWD, DB,...
        </programlisting>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="gatekeeper-related-items">
    <title>Related Links</title>

    <para>Lots of other web sites do related things.  For example, anonymizer sites allow
    you to surf the web while doing seamless translation of the page.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.anonymizer.com">Anonymizer Site</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="gatekeeper-functional-requirements">
      <title>Functional Requirements</title>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Req #</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Priority</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Status in 5.0</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Description</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>10.0</entry>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>?</entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Seamless
              Viewing</emphasis>. The gatekeeper should provide seamless viewing of URLs.  This means
              that the URLs should look like they belong to the ACS site, not the
              original site.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>Does this refer to web pages or to URL?  Ie, does this mean that "user can click on a link and see (password-protected) web pages from a remote site, within the OpenACS site's look and feel," or does it mean, "user can click URLs that look like http://myopenacssite.test/foo/bar"?</para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>20.0</entry>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>?</entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Restricted Browsing</emphasis>. 
A given instance of the gatekeeper package should only provide access
    to a single site.  The user must not be able to modify the URL so that
    arbitrary sites can be retrieved through the server.
</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>


      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>30.0</entry>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>?</entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Link Translation</emphasis>. 
 All links from the gatekeeper page to the given site should be
    translated to use the gatekeeper.
</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>40.0</entry>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>?</entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">User Tracking</emphasis>. 
The ability to track all pages viewed via the gatekeeper should exist.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">50.0 Flexible Restrictions</emphasis>
    </para>
    <blockquote>
    <para><emphasis role="strong">50.1 ACS Permissions</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    The gatekeeper package should support standard ACS permissioning.  Access can thus
    be limited by setting up limited read access to an instance of the gatekeeper package.
    </para>
    <para><emphasis role="strong">50.2 Callbacks </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    The gatekeepers should be provide access control via registered callbacks.
    </para>
    </blockquote>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">60.0 Full HTTP Support</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
    The gatekeeper should support the entire HTTP specification.
    <blockquote>
        <para><emphasis role="strong">60.1 POST Support</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        POST form submission must be supported.
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="strong">60.2 Non-HTML Pages</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        Retrieval of non-HTML pages, such as GIFs and JPEGs, must be supported.
        </para>
        <para><emphasis role="strong">60.3 Cookie Support</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        The system should have the ability to store and respond with cookies sent
        from the guarded site.
        </para>
    </blockquote>
    </para>


    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="gatekeeper-revisions-history">
      <title>Revision History</title>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Document Revision #</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">Action Taken, Notes</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">When?</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="strong">By Whom?</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1</entry>
              <entry>Creation</entry>
              <entry>23 Nov 2000</entry>
              <entry>Joseph Bank</entry>
            </row>
            
            <row>
              <entry>2</entry>
              <entry>Revised to add Nima Mazloumi's use case.</entry>
              <entry>13 Jan 2004</entry>
              <entry>Joel Aufrecht</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>